<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
   Copyright 2015 CrudFaces.

   Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
   the License. You may obtain a copy of the License at

	   http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software distributed under the License is distributed on
  an "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied. See the License for the
  specific language governing permissions and limitations under the License.
-->
<facelet-taglib id="cf"
                xmlns="http://xmlns.jcp.org/xml/ns/javaee"
                xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
                xsi:schemaLocation="http://xmlns.jcp.org/xml/ns/javaee http://xmlns.jcp.org/xml/ns/javaee/web-facelettaglibrary_2_2.xsd"
                version="2.2"
>
    <description>CrudFaces UI components.</description>
    <namespace>http://crudfaces.codebulb.ch</namespace>
    <short-name>cf</short-name>
	
    <tag>
        <description>
			<![CDATA[
				<p>
A container component to apply implicitly "form-like" (e.g. label / input /
message) grid styling of its child components using a (responsive) CSS layout
with out-of-the-box support for Bootstrap responsive form grid CSS classes.
</p>
<p>
Modern interface stying is based on CSS, not HTML tables, because it embraces
separation of design and functionality, and it enables sophisticated
techniques such as responsive, mobile-friendly layouts. </p>
<p>
However, none of today's available JSF (component) frameworks deliver an
easy-to-use abstraction for styling components using these techniques. The
built-in containers for JSF and PrimeFaces, e.g.
<code>&lt;panelGrid&gt;</code>, are based on HTML tables. PrimeFaces provides
<a href="http://www.primefaces.org/showcase/ui/panel/grid.xhtml">
an additional set of CSS grid classes</a>, but they don't seem to actually
work responsively at all; also, they need to be applied explicitly.</p>
<p>
This is especially annoying as most JSF web applications typically make heavy
use of quite simple grid-like form layouts, but using
<code>&lt;panelGrid&gt;</code> or applying HTML tables / CSS explicitly is
cumbersome and diminishes XHTML readability, especially when trying to align
components in a certain way or when using "colspan" attributes. What we
really want is a panelGrid, but which works with CSS classes and is built
with responsiveness out-of-the box. This is what
<code>&lt;cf:formLayout&gt;</code> provides.</p>
<p>
A <a href="http://www.bootsfaces.net/layout/panelgrids.jsf">similar component
is also included in the BootsFaces library</a>, but it seems far more basic
and doesn't come as real-world production-ready as
 <code>&lt;cf:formLayout&gt;</code>.</p>
<p>
<code>&lt;cf:formLayout&gt;</code> implicitly applies the required CSS
classes to its child components to build a simple form-like grid layout for a
flexible amount of columns (default 2). It is preconfigured to use
Bootstrap's form-horizontal styling CSS classes with its base 12 grid
system.</p>
<p>
<code>&lt;cf:formLayout&gt;</code> also includes the following features:</p>
<ul>
<li><code>&lt;message&gt;</code>s are combined with their respective input
component into one cell. This is typically desired because otherwise,
non-present messages (which still render an empty cell) would create huge
gaps in the UI.</li>
<li>Buttons are by default put in a "button bar" at the bottom of the layout.
If you want a particular button to stay inline, add the
<code>a:inline="true"</code> HTML5 pass-through attribute to it. If on the
other hand you want a non-button component to be placed in the "button bar",
use the <code>a:buttonBar="true"</code> pass-through attribute.</li>
</ul>
<p>
Note that <code>&lt;cf:formLayout&gt;</code> does not implement an actual
HTML <code>&lt;form&gt;</code>, it's really just for layouting purposes which
leaves you the free choice of how to integrate it in an actual HTML form.</p>
<h2>Known restrictions</h2>
<ul>
<li>Nesting <code>&lt;cf:formLayout&gt;</code>s is not supported.</li>
<li>Support for custom styling is very limited; explicitly override the
default styles is not supported.</li>
</ul>
<p>
These restrictions are most likely to be addressed and resolved in future
CrudFaces versions.</p>
			]]>
        </description>
        <tag-name>formLayout</tag-name>
        <component>
            <component-type>ch.codebulb.crudfaces.component.FormLayout</component-type>
        </component>
        <attribute>
            <description>
				<![CDATA[
					<p>The number of groups per row. <i>Defaults to <code>1</code>.</i></p>
					<p>Components are organized in groups, and groups are aligned in rows. This matches Bootstrap's grid system which requires
					components to be combined in <code>form-group</code>s for use with validation styling. Use <code>groupRatios</code> to control the number of components per group.</p>
				]]>
            </description>
            <name>groups</name>
            <required>false</required>
            <type>java.lang.Integer</type>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
            <description>
				<![CDATA[
					<p>The aspect ratio of the components in one group, separated by a whitespace character. <i>Defaults to <code>"4 8"</code>.</i></p>
					<p>Components are organized in groups. Typically, a group consists of a label,
					an input component and optional helper components such as a help button. The number of individual numbers in <code>groupRatios</code> determines the number of components per group;
					their respective aspect ratio determines their actual aspect ratio whereby the total number should match the container's max aspect ratio. For a Bootstrap container, this is <code>12</code>.</p>
				]]>
            </description>
            <name>groupRatios</name>
            <required>false</required>
            <type>java.lang.String</type>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
            <description>
				<![CDATA[
					<p>The component style class. <i>Defaults to <code>null</code>.</i></p>
					<p>If present, this style class is added to the outermost container's <code>class</code> attribute.</p>
				]]>
            </description>
            <name>styleClass</name>
            <required>false</required>
            <type>java.lang.String</type>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
            <description>
				<![CDATA[
					<p>The component inline style. <i>Defaults to <code>null</code>.</i></p>
					<p>If present, this style is added to the outermost container's <code>style</code> attribute.</p>
				]]>
            </description>
            <name>style</name>
            <required>false</required>
            <type>java.lang.String</type>
        </attribute>
    </tag>
    <tag>
        <description>
			<![CDATA[
				<p>
A componenthandler tag which turns all (deep) nested input components into
&lt;h:outputText&gt; components, thus rendering the "read only" equivalent.
</p>
<p>
Although vanilla JSF provides the <code>disabled</code> attribute for every
component, this attribute still renders the component in question as true
input component, but grays it out such that the user cannot manipulate it.
However, this does not cover the typical use-case of providing both a "write"
and a "read" mode for a component or even an entire view as this view is
expected to be presented as a true plain HTML output text. This is what is
achieved by using the
<code>&lt;cf:readOnly&gt;</code> tag.</p>
<p>
This component is realized as a simple JSF component, but with the special
<code>ReadOnly</code> componenthandler attached which executes the actual
transformation. Because the <code>id</code> attribute is kept if explicitly
set for the original input component, it can still be targetted by e.g. an
<code>&lt;outputLabel&gt;</code>, a
<code>&lt;message&gt;</code>, or a <code>&lt;p:focus&gt;</code> component,
hence preventing "target not found" errors.</p>
<h2>Usage</h2>
<p>
Using the tag is somewhat similar to OmniFaces'
<code>&lt;o:massAttribute&gt;</code> tag: Just surround the component(s) in
question with the tag. Of course, you can switch between input and output
rendering conditionally using the component's <code>disabled</code>
attribute.</p>

<h2>Known restrictions</h2>
<ul>
<li>Only simple text input PrimeFaces components are supported.</li>
</ul>
<p>
These restrictions are most likely to be addressed and resolved in future
CrudFaces versions.</p>
			]]>
        </description>
        <tag-name>readOnly</tag-name>
        <component>
            <component-type>ch.codebulb.crudfaces.component.ReadOnly</component-type>
            <handler-class>ch.codebulb.crudfaces.componenthandler.ReadOnly</handler-class>
        </component>
        <attribute>
            <description>
				<![CDATA[
					<p><code>true</code> to disable the functionality. <i>Defaults to <code>false</code>.</i></p>
				]]>
            </description>
            <name>disabled</name>
            <required>false</required>
            <type>java.lang.Boolean</type>
        </attribute>
    </tag>
	
</facelet-taglib>